I belong to a family of very enlightened people. My father was linguist and he was
मैं एक बहुत प्रबुद्ध परिवार से ताल्लुक रखती हूँ। मेरे पिता भाषाविद् थे और वे
master of 14 languages. He knew about 26 languages and he translated even Quran-e-Sharif
14 भाषाओं में माहिर थे। वह करीब 26 भाषाएँ जानते थे और उन्होंने कुरान-ए-शरीफ का भी अनुवाद
into Hindi language. My mother was, in those days, was a honors in Mathematics.
हिंदी भाषा में किया। मेरी माँ, उन दिनों में, गणित में प्रावीण्य थीं।
So, both were very well educated and enlightened people. At the time of My birth,
इसलिए, दोनों बहुत पढ़े-लिखे और प्रबुद्ध लोग थे । मेरे जन्म के वक्त,
My mother dreamt something which she could not explain but after that she had a great
मेरी माँ ने कुछ सपना देखा जो वह समझा नहीं पाईं, लेकिन उसके बाद उन्हें,
desire to go and see a tiger in the open field. My father was a great hunter because
खुले मैदान में, बाघ को देखने जाने की तीव्र इच्छा हुई। मेरे पिता एक महान शिकारी थे और
tigers were a menace in the area where we were living, it was a hill station called
बाघ उस क्षेत्र में एक खतरा थे जहां हम रह रहे थे। यह एक हिल स्टेशन था जिसका नाम
Chhindwara. So there was a king, who was very much interested in my father. Somehow
छिंदवाड़ा था। तो एक राजा थे, जो मेरे पिताजी में बहुत रुचि रखते थे। किसी न किसी
or other a letter came that, "There's a tiger, very big tiger that has appeared
तरह, एक पत्र आया कि, "यहाँ एक बाघ, बहुत बड़ा बाघ दिखाई दिया है
and they're frightened of him that he might be a man-eater." So, My father took
और हम सब उससे भयभीत हैं कि वह आदमखोर हो सकता है।" तो, मेरे पिता
My mother and Me to that place and they were sitting, what we call, as a machaan,
मेरी माँ और मुझे उस स्थान पर ले गए और वह लोग बैठे, जिसे हम मचान कहते हैं,
where they built something for people to sit on top of a tree from where they can
जहां उन्होंने, एक पेड़ के ऊपर लोगों के बैठने के लिए कुछ बनाया, जहाँ से वे
shoot nicely. And then My mother tells Me that a big, huge tiger of a very big size
अच्छी तरह से गोली चला सकें। और फिर, मेरी माँ मुझसे कहती हैं कि, बहुत बड़े आकार का एक बड़ा, विशाल बाघ
very beautifully appeared on the field and she felt tremendous love for the tiger.
मैदान पर बहुत ही खूबसूरती से दिखाई दिया और उन्हें बाघ के प्रति असीम प्रेम का अनुभव हुआ।
It was a full moon day and she felt extremely compassionate towards the tiger
वह पूर्णिमा का दिन था और उन्हें बाघ के प्रति अत्यंत करुणा महसूस हुई
and when My father raised his gun to shoot, she stopped him and she wouldn't allow him
और जब मेरे पिता ने गोली चलाने के लिए अपनी बन्दूक उठाई, उन्होंने उन्हें रोका और उन्हें अनुमति नहीं दी
and the tiger went away and he never came to that forest again but that made
और बाघ चला गया और वह कभी उस जंगल में फिर से नहीं आया लेकिन
My father think because he himself was a realized soul that must be somebody,
उससे मेरे पिता को विचार आया, क्योंकि वह स्वयं एक प्रबुद्ध आत्मा थे कि, अवश्य कोई होना चाहिए,
what we call a Goddess Durga, who's fond of a tiger, must be born to My mother because
जिन्हें हम देवी दुर्गा कहते हैं, जिन्हें बाघ प्रिय है, मेरी माँ की कोख से जन्म ले रहीं हैं क्योंकि
the symptoms were rather funny that a lady should like to see a tiger and all.
लक्षण कुछ विचित्र थे कि कोई महिला एक बाघ को देखना पसंद करे।
So, he told My mother, "Now, are you satisfied because they were struggling with the gun."
तो, उन्होंने मेरी माँ से कहा, "अब, क्या आप संतुष्ट हैं," क्योंकि वे बंदूक के साथ संघर्ष कर रहे थे।
He said, "Is there a Durga sitting in your womb that you are trying to protect the tiger?"
उन्होंने कहा, "क्या आपके गर्भ में कोई दुर्गा बैठी हैं कि आप बाघ की रक्षा करने की कोशिश कर रही हो?"
She said, "Yes, yes, so stop it now. I won't allow you." Like that there were
वह बोलीं, "हाँ, हाँ, तो इसे अभी बंद करें। मैं आपको अनुमति नहीं दूँगी।" ऐसे ही
many incidents in My life because I'm of a Christian family, Protestants and when
मेरे जीवन में कई घटनाएं थीं क्योंकि मैं एक ईसाई परिवार से हूँ, प्रोटेस्टेंट और
I was born, My mother didn't feel any labor pains or anything and just I was born, She
जब मेरा जन्म हुआ, मेरी माँ को कोई प्रसव पीड़ा नहीं हुई, दर्द या कुछ भी और बस मैं पैदा हो गयी। उन्हें
didn't know how and I had no blood on My body, nothing. I was clean washed that's why
पता नहीं था कैसे और मेरे शरीर पर कोई खून नहीं लगा था, कुछ भी नहीं। मैं साफ धुली हुई थी इसीलिए
they called My name as Nirmala but My grandmother said that, "She should be
उन्होंने मेरा नाम निर्मला रखा लेकिन मेरी दादी ने कहा कि, "उसे
called as Nishkalanka - that means 'The one which has no spots on it' but that's
निष्कलंक कहा जाना चाहिए - जिसका अर्थ है 'वह जिस पर कोई धब्बे नहीं हैं' लेकिन वह
the name of a man, so they said, "Alright, we'll call Her Nirmala, meaning the same,
एक आदमी का नाम  है, तो उन्होंने कहा, "ठीक है, हम उसे निर्मला कहेंगे, जिसका अर्थ भी वही है,
Immaculata." Now all these incidents and then My father being a realized soul,
बेदाग।" अब ये सारी घटनाएँ और फिर मेरे पिता के एक प्रबुद्ध आत्मा होने के कारण,
he felt tremendous vibrations from Me and he felt that this life is great and She
उन्होंने मुझ से जबरदस्त चैतन्य महसूस किया और उन्हें लगा कि मेरा यह जीवन महान है और मैं
will do something great in this life. I do not know why but I don't know if he dreamt
इस जीवन में कुछ महान कार्य करुँगी। मुझे पता नहीं क्यों लेकिन मुझे नहीं पता कि क्या उन्होंने सपना देखा था
or he understood it but all the time, if I remember, when he talked to Me, he used
या वह इसे समझ गए थे लेकिन हर समय, अगर मुझे याद है, जब भी वह मुझसे बात करते थे, वह
to say that, "You have to find out a way of giving enmasse realization," all the time.
हर समय यह कहते थे, "आपको सामूहिक साक्षात्कार देने का एक रास्ता खोजना होगा।"
As I told you, he was a great scholar of so many things and a very widely read man,
जैसा कि मैंने आपको बताया, वह इतनी सारी चीज़ों के एक महान विद्वान थे और बहुत व्यापक रूप से शिक्षित व्यक्ति थे,
so he gave Me a good education in religion, in different religions and also
इसलिए उन्होंने मुझे धर्म में एक अच्छी शिक्षा दी, विभिन्न धर्मों में और
good education about human-beings, what are their problems, why they react like this,
मनुष्यों के बारे में भी अच्छी शिक्षा, उनकी समस्याएं क्या हैं, वे इस तरह प्रतिक्रिया क्यों करते हैं,
why don't they take to God, why are they hypocritical, all kinds of things he
वे भगवान के रास्ते को क्यों नहीं अपनाते, वे पाखंडी क्यों हैं, हर तरह की बातें
talked to Me. He also knew about Kundalini but not so much. Of course, when I was
मुझसे कीं। उन्हें कुंडलिनी के बारे में भी पता था लेकिन उतना नहीं। बेशक, जब मेरा
born, I knew about Kundalini Myself, I knew all about it from My very childhood.
जन्म हुआ, मैं स्वयं कुंडलिनी के बारे में जानती थी, इसके बारे में मुझे बचपन से ही पता था।
I was very aware person, extremely aware but I didn't know whom to talk to because
मैं बहुत जागरूक व्यक्ति थी, बेहद जागरूक लेकिन मुझे नहीं पता था कि किससे बात करूँ क्योंकि
you see people didn't have that awareness; You can't talk to everyone like that.
आप देखें कि लोगों में वह जागरूकता नहीं थी; आप सभी से इस तरह बात नहीं कर सकते।
So, I was regarded as a very jolly person, at the same time, very serious also
इसलिए, मुझे एक बहुत ही हंसमुख व्यक्ति माना जाता था, साथ ही, बहुत गंभीर,
very deep and then I started My studies as a child.
बहुत गहन भी और फिर मैंने एक बच्चे के रूप में अपनी पढ़ाई शुरू की।